Finding Aid for Kenneth Thorpe Rowe Papers 1940-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kenneth Thorpe Rowe Papers 1940-1953
Rowe, Kenneth Thorpe, 1900-1988
Professor of drama at University of Michigan, chairman of the Committee on War Activities of the American Educational Theatre Association, and secretary of the Theatre for Victory Council during World War II. Files concerning his war activities, including correspondence, scripts, course materials and printed matter; and photographs.
852167 Aa 2
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Rowe (Donor no. 5058 ) and came to the library in April 1971.
The collection is open for research.
Kenneth Thorpe Rowe, professor of drama at the University of Michigan, was born in Iowa City, Iowa in 1900. He attended Rice Institute, receiving his A.B. and M.A. degrees from there in 1922. Rowe received a second Master's degree from Harvard University in 1927.
Before coming to the University of Michigan, Rowe taught two years at the Rice Institute followed by four years at the University of Oregon. Offered an associate professorship by the University of Michigan English department Rowe came to Ann Arbor in 1928. This began an association between Rowe and the University of Michigan which lasted nearly forty years.
The Kenneth Rowe Collection, though covering the period 1940-1953, largely concerns the years of World War II and the activities of Rove as chairman of the Committee on War Activities for the American Educational Theatre Association (AETA); as secretary of the Theatre for Victory Council; as consultant to the National Theatre Conference (NTC), official agency for all dramatic activities of the Combined Armed Forces; and as drama consultant to the U.S. Department of Treasury, the Office of Civil Defense, and the Office of Education. Rowe's work in all of these efforts concerned the use of drama as a propaganda tool to raise morale and to define America's goals.
The Rowe collection consists of two linear feet of correspondence, reports, newsletters, play scripts, and printed material. The collection begins with general correspondence followed by files which have been arranged by the name of theatre organizations in which Rove was involved.
Subjects:
American Educational Theatre Association.; American Educational Theatre Association. Committee on War Activities.; Rowe, Kenneth Thorpe, 1900-1988; Theater--United States.; Theatre for Victory Council.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Classrooms.; Costumes.; Patriotism.; Rowe, Kenneth Thorpe, 1900-1988; Schools--Wisconsin.; Theatrical productions.; Wisconsin--Schools.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (1-1)
- Correspondence and other papers
  - January 1942-March 1944, 13 folders (Box 1)
    (1-2 to 1-14)
  - Correspondence with E.C. Mabie, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-15; 1-16)
- American National Theatre Assembly
  - Papers 1945-1953, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (1-17 to 1-19)
  - Newsletters 1947-1952, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-20; 1-21)
- National Theatre Conference
  - Papers 1942-1950, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (1-22 to 1-24)
  - Annual Convention 1945, 1947, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (1-25 to 1-27)
  - Annual Report New Playwright Project (Box 1)
    (1-28)
  - Quarterly Bulletin Article: "Facts for the Future" (Box 1)
    (1-29)
  - Listings of Plays 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    (1-30)
  - Armed Forces Institute
    - Papers 1943-1944 (Box 1)
      (1-31)
    - Conference Report 1943 (Box 1)
      (1-32)
    - Mini Course Outline (Box 1)
      (1-33)
    - Playwriting Contest (Box 1)
      (1-34)
- American Educational Theatre Association
  - Papers 1941-1949 (Box 1)
    (1-35)
  - Annual Report 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-36;1-37)
  - Annual Convention
    - 1940, 1941, 1943, 1945 (Box 1)
      (1-38)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
      (1-39)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
      (1-40)
  - Membership list 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    (1-41)
  - Report to National Theatre Conference Advisory Committee (Box 1)
    (1-42)
  - Manuscript play project (Box 1)
    (1-43)
  - Playwriting and Production of New Plays Committee
    - Correspondence 1942 (Box 1)
      (1-44)
    - Membership list (Box 1)
      (1-45)
    - Work Program (Box 1)
      (1-46)
  - Progress and Planning Committee
    - Papers November 1944-July 1945 (Box 1)
      (1-47)
    - Report (Box 1)
      (1-48)
  - Newsletters 1942-1944, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (1-49; 1-50)
  - Film News 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    (1-51)
  - Committee on War Activities
    - Papers (Box 2)
      (2-1)
    - Reports 1943, 1942 (Box 2)
      (2-2)
    - Army bibliography; letters received by H. Bricker from Armed Services later forwarded to K. Rowe 1944 (Box 2)
      (2-3)
    - Army Bibliography Correspondence 1944 (Box 2)
      (2-4)
    - Treasury Scripts 1944 (Box 2)
      (2-5)
    - Office of War Information Mailing List (Box 2)
      (2-6)
    - Theatre
      - Papers 1942-1943 (Box 2)
        (2-7)
      - Reports (Box 2)
        (2-8)
      - Research materials (Box 2)
        (2-9)
    - Request made for scripts to aid war effort (Box 2)
      (2-10)
    - University of Michigan Student War Scripts
      - Papers 1943 (Box 2)
        (2-11)
      - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (2-12; 2-13)
      - "Wilson Family" 1942 (Box 2)
        (2-14)
      - "The Good Land" 1943 (Box 2)
        (2-15)
      - "Battle Song of Freedom 1942-1943 (Box 2)
        (2-16)
      - "Song for Victory" 1943 (Box 2)
        (2-17)
      - "Thanksgiving Proclaimed" 1943 (Box 2)
        (2-18)
    - High School Project
      - Papers 1942-1943 (Box 2)
        (2-19)
      - Wauwatosa High School 1943 (Box 2)
        (2-20)
      - Printed materials (Box 2)
        (2-21)
      - The Communication Arts in the High School Victory Corp. (Box 2)
        (2-22)
    - Theatre for Victory (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1943 (Box 2)
      (2-23)
    - Reorganization 1944 (Box 2)
      (2-24)
    - Seattle Civilian War Commission
      - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (2-25; 2-26)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        (2-27)
- Miscellaneous
  - American Theatre Wing, Inc. 1950 (Box 2)
    (2-28)
  - University of Michigan Drama Class (Box 2)
    (2-29)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    Photographs included items depicting the High School Theatre for Victory program at Wauwatosa High School, Wauwatosa, Wisconsin; and portraits.